<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>RDM@UPorto</title>
    <link>https://rdm.up.pt/tags/deposit/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on RDM@UPorto</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright (c) 2016, UPorto, all rights reserved.</copyright>
    <atom:link href="https://rdm.up.pt/tags/deposit/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>DATA MANAGEMENT</title>
      <link>https://rdm.up.pt/Resources%20Tools%20Data%20Management%20Dendro/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2015 21:49:20 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rdm.up.pt/Resources%20Tools%20Data%20Management%20Dendro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Dendro is a collaborative tool developed under the scope of a doctoral thesis in the Faculty of Engineering of University of Porto with the aim to help researchers to integrate the data management in the research workflow. Its essence relies in the use of specific domain ontologies to describe the data created so that this remains “alive” for a long period of time. This means that data becomes sharable at the end of the research process and re-usable by other researchers.
Dendro interacts with Ckan, the digital platform where the University of Porto implemented its data repository - at the end of a research process, the authors send the final datasets and some privileged metadata to Ckan, where data will be available for future reuse in accordance to the licenses chosen by their authors.&lt;br /&gt;
Dendro is currently being tested with research groups of the University of Porto.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>RESEARCH MANAGERS</title>
      <link>https://rdm.up.pt/stakeholders/2015/10/02/research-managers/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2015 21:49:20 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rdm.up.pt/stakeholders/2015/10/02/research-managers/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Research data managers play a key role throughout research projects in ensuring that data is usable in the future. They provide guidance to researchers in preparing data for sharing by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Providing assistance with the preparation of data management plans&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Suggesting the use of metadata standards to enable the reuse of data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Providing guidance in the use of online tools&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identificating the appropriate repository to publish the research outputs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Electing the appropriate licenses, considering the type of data involved&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section contains answers to the most frequently asked questions posed by research data managers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-data-should-be-published&#34;&gt;What data should be published?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All kind of data are candidate for sharing, but unique data or expensive to generate are especially important; they may become a valuable asset. As a minimum, it should be published the research data that are expected to be valuable to others, that can testify and validate findings, and that help researchers to increase recognition in the community. Moreover, the contracts signed between researchers and funder agencies establihs the requirements of data deposit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-data-curation&#34;&gt;What is data curation?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data curation involves maintaining, preserving and adding value to data research troughout the data life cycle, reducing the threat of devaluation, or even data loss. It also reduces duplication of effort in creating research data, freeing researchers to other activities.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>