<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>RDM@UPorto</title>
    <link>https://rdm.up.pt/tags/researchers/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on RDM@UPorto</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright (c) 2016, UPorto, all rights reserved.</copyright>
    <atom:link href="https://rdm.up.pt/tags/researchers/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>RESEARCHERS</title>
      <link>https://rdm.up.pt/stakeholders/2015/10/10/researchers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Oct 2015 13:07:31 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://rdm.up.pt/stakeholders/2015/10/10/researchers/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;This section contains answers to the most frequently asked questions presented by researchers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to manage and publish research data?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where to find a trusted platform to publish the data of a specific domain?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which are the national and institutional policies and strategies concerning the sharing of data?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How to make compliant the confidentiality inherent of certain types of data to the requirements of sharing data?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where can I find advice about which data should I keep and which data will not be necessary for further use?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where can find to design a data management plan?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;if-i-adopt-dendro-and-its-processes-what-extra-effort-do-i-have-to-account-for-in-my-project&#34;&gt;If I adopt Dendro and its processes, what extra effort do I have to account for in my project?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you already have data that are generated and shared in your project, you are already using project manpower in RDM, albeit informally. You can improve your process with the Dendro workflow, creating metadata according to the standards in your domain and preparing the datasets to be ready for publication any time you decide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-should-i-spend-extra-time-managing-my-data-now-that-my-results-are-out&#34;&gt;Why should I spend extra time managing my data, now that my results are out?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More and more, the time for data management will be distributed from the project proposal to the final presentation of results. But for important results where your research has impact, you can invest in preparing and publishing datasets, improving your visibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-do-i-need-to-describe-my-data&#34;&gt;Why do I need to describe my data?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Data in a repository can be hard to find and, when someone finds them and wants to reuse them, they need to know about the data production context. Considering that research data, unlike publications, may provide no clue as to its nature, resorting to metadata will promote data discovery, interpretation, preservation and further reuse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-kinds-of-data-are-candidates-for-sharing&#34;&gt;What kinds of data are candidates for sharing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Potentially all kinds of data are candidates for sharing, but unique data are especially important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;do-i-have-to-share-all-my-research-data&#34;&gt;Do I have to share all my research data?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should share the research data that is necessary to validate findings described in your publications, data which might be valuable to others, data which cannot be re-generated, …&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;do-i-need-to-share-data-underpinning-my-doctoral-thesis&#34;&gt;Do I need to share data underpinning my doctoral thesis?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You are encouraged to do so, providing that the research process is not damaged by premature and/or inappropriate release of research data. For example, if you release your data, you might be unable to use it in future publications. In general, it is advised that supervisors be always consulted before any research data underpinning PhD research is released.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;can-i-restrict-access-to-my-data&#34;&gt;Can I restrict access to my data?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most funders expect publicly funded research data to be made freely available, with as few restrictions as possible. However, there are some exemptions to this:
- Personal/sensitive data should not be released into public domain, unless consent of the person is given and data is properly anonymised;
- Delays/restrictions are acceptable if necessary to protect IP or commercially confidential data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;if-data-preservation-is-not-possible-or-cost-effective-it-is-acceptable-not-to-publish-the-data-as-long-as-the-ability-to-validate-published-research-findings-is-not-compromised-and-the-access-to-data-might-be-granted-in-other-ways&#34;&gt;If data preservation is not possible or cost-effective, it is acceptable not to publish the data, as long as the ability to validate published research findings is not compromised and the access to data might be granted in other ways.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;can-i-submit-my-data-to-any-repository-i-want&#34;&gt;Can I submit my data to any repository I want?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your research is funded, you may be required to submit your data to a repository suggested by your funder. Otherwise, it is up to you and your research group to choose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;are-my-data-safe-in-a-repository&#34;&gt;Are my data safe in a repository?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should be concerned with that, and look for a trusted digital repository for your data. In case that is not available, you need to assess the plans and the expected evolution of the repository you are planning to use. There are some initiatives, such as the Data Seal of Approval, that certify data repositories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-am-involved-in-a-collaborative-project-with-researchers-who-do-not-want-to-share-data-what-should-i-do&#34;&gt;I am involved in a collaborative project with researchers who do not want to share data. What should I do?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideally (and in future collaborations), you should inform your potential collaborators that due to your public funding, you are expected to share research data as openly as possible. With your current research project, you should determine with your collaborators which data can be shared. If some research data need to be restricted, then you should provide an appropriate statement in your publication explaining the reason why access to data is not open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-if-someone-uses-my-data-improperly&#34;&gt;What if someone uses my data improperly?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is unfortunately always possible and cannot be avoided. Every time you publish, you risk being misinterpreted – that is also true in the traditional publication process. Publishing research data underpinning your publication actually decreases the risk of your work being misinterpreted or misused, as you can be more transparent about your research findings. Remember to choose a proper license for your data – the type of license will determine what people can do with your research data. Read more about licenses here: ….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-do-i-get-credit-for-my-data&#34;&gt;How do I get credit for my data?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The publication of research data helps to increase the visibility and accessibility of all research results. The reuse of data favours their citation and that of associated papers. The academic and scientific community is now more motivated to recognize non-standard research outputs such as data, code and professional network activities. Sharing data can also foster the partnership with other researchers or institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>